[
    {
        "question": "The first muslim woman who ruled Northern India was",
        "options": [
            "Razia Sultana",
            "Nurjahan",
            "Mumtaz",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Razia, the Only Muslim Woman Ruler of India. She was Born on October 1205 in Budaun, Mughal empress Razia Sultana was given the name Raziyya al-Din upon birth. She became the only women ruler of Delhi Sultanate in Mughal era to make such history."
    },
    {
        "question": "The silver coin 'tanka' was introduced by",
        "options": [
            "Qutub-ud-din Aibak",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Bairam Khan"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "Iltutmish introduced Silver Tanka and Copper Jital, the two coins of the Delhi Sultanate. The coins prior to Iltutmish were introduced by the invaders which bear the Sanskrit characters and even Bull and Shivalinga. Iltutmish was the first to introduce a “Pure Arabic Coin” in India."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which battle did open the Delhi area to Muhammad Ghori?",
        "options": [
            "First Battle of Tarain",
            "Second Battle of Tarain",
            "Battle of Khanwa",
            "First Battle of Panipat"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "The Battles of Tarain, also known as the Battles of Taraori, were fought in 1191 and 1192 near the town of Tarain (Taraori), near Thanesar in present-day Haryana, approximately 150 kilometres north of Delhi, India, between a Ghurid force led by Mu'izz al-Din and a Chauhan Rajput army led by Prithviraj Chauhan."
    },
    {
        "question": "To take care of the conquered lands, Muhmmad Ghori left behind his trusted General",
        "options": [
            "Nasiruddin",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Qutub-din-Aibak",
            "Malik Kafur"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "Ghori treated his slaves very nicely and sometimes with as much affection as a father would have for his son. One of his slaves was Qutb-ud-din Aibak. With the time, he rose through the ranks to become the most trusted general of Ghori. His greatest military successes occurred while working directly under Ghori's leadership. He was left with independent charge of Indian campaigns and thus became the first Muslim emperor of Northern India. He also established Turkish rule in India and made Delhi and Lahore his capital cities."
    },
    {
        "question": "The first Sultan who requested and obtained letters of investiture from the Caliph (Khalifa) was",
        "options": [
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Firoz Tughlaq",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "The first Sultan who requested and obtained letters of investiture from the Khalifa was Iltutmish. The government established by the Turks was a compromise between Islamic Political Ideas and institutions on the one hand and the existing Rajput System of Government on the other."
    },
    {
        "question": "Muhammad Ghori laid the foundation of the Turkish Empire in India by defeating",
        "options": [
            "Prithviraj Chauhan in Second Battle of Tarain",
            "Jayachanda in the Battle of Chandawar",
            "The Chandelas",
            "Both (A) and (B) above"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "d",
        "note": "Muhammad Ghori laid the foundation of the Turkish Empire in India by defeating Prithviraj Chauhan in Second Battle of Tarain and Jayachanda in the Battle of Chandawar. Mahmud of Ghazni also failed to set up a Muslim empire in India and the only permanent effect of his invasions was the annexation of Punjab. It was left to Muhammad Ghori to build up a Muslim empire in India on a secure footing in 1173 A.D."
    },
    {
        "question": "Where had Qutub-ud-din Aibak got constructed the Adhai-din-ka Jhonpra (Hut of Two-and-a-half- Days)?",
        "options": [
            "Agra",
            "Ajmer",
            "Delhi",
            "Fatehpur Sikri"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "Adhai Din Ka Jhonpra is a mosque in the Ajmer city of Rajasthan, India. It was commissioned by Qutb-ud-Din-Aibak, on orders of Muhammad Ghori, in 1192 CE. It was completed in 1199 CE, and further beautified by Iltutmish of Delhi in 1213 CE."
    },
    {
        "question": "Iltutmish established a centre of learning at",
        "options": [
            "Multan",
            "Calcutta",
            "Alwar",
            "Delhi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "d",
        "note": "Iltutmish was the prominent ruler of slave dynasty of Delhi Sultanate. During his reign Delhi became an important centre of learning and culture in the East."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who defeated whom in the second Battle of Tarain (AD 1192)?",
        "options": [
            "Prithviraj defeated Muhammad Ghori",
            "Mahmud Ghazni defeated Prithviraj",
            "Prithviraj defeated Mahmud Ghazni",
            "Muhammad Ghori defeated Prithviraj"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "d",
        "note": "The Second Battle of Tarain (Taraori) was again fought between Ghurid army of Mohammed Ghori and Rajput army of Prithviraj Chauhan. The battle took place in 1192 A.D near Tarain. In this battle, Prithviraj Chauhan was defeated by Mohammed Ghori."
    },
    {
        "question": "The culmination of the series of the uprisings was the Mappila revolt of",
        "options": [
            "1921",
            "1895",
            "1821",
            "1721"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Mappila Riots or Mappila Outbreaks refers to a series of riots by the Mappila (Moplah) Muslims of Malabar, South India in the 19th century and the early 20th century (c.1836–1921) against native Hindus and the state. The Malabar Rebellion of 1921 is often considered as the culmination of Mappila riots."
    },
    {
        "question": "The battle that led to the foundation of Muslim power in India was",
        "options": [
            "The first battle of Tarain",
            "The second battle of Tarain",
            "The first battle of Panipat",
            "The second battle of Panipat"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "The second battle of Tarain was fought near Thaneswar (Haryana) in 1192 A.D., between the Rajput Army under Prithviraj Chauhan and the army of Muhammad Ghori. Prithviraj Chauhan was defeated by Ghori in this battle and this paved the way of Muslim Rule in India."
    },
    {
        "question": "When the rule of the Delhi sultanate began?",
        "options": [
            "1106 A.D.",
            "1206 A.D.",
            "1306 A.D.",
            "1406 A.D."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "The rule of the Delhi sultanate began from 1206 to 1526."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Saviour of the Delhi Sultanate was",
        "options": [
            "Qutub-din-Aibak",
            "Minas-us-Siraj",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Ghiyasuddin Balban"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "d",
        "note": "Giyasuddin Balban came upon the throne at a time when the Delhi Sultanate had fallen into utter confusion due to the incompetence of the successors of Iltutmish. The country was subjected to foreign attacks. he reorganized the armed forces and thorough reforms were introduced in civil administration. Under his orders new strong fortresses were built in the north-western frontier. He saved the Sultanate from impending disintegration. So he should be considered as the ‘savior of the Delhi Sultanate’."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is known as the \"slave of a slave\"?",
        "options": [
            "Muhammad bin Oasim",
            "Mahmud of Ghazni",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Outbuddin Aibak"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "Iltutmish, a “slave of a slave” is regarded by several historians as the real founder and consolidator of the slave Dynasty and the Delhi Sultanate. According to them, Aibak was the ruler for four years only."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Delhi Sultan who fell to his death while playing polo was",
        "options": [
            "Qutb-din-Aibak",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Feroz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Qutb-ud-din Aibak died in an accident while he was playing polo. He fell from a horse and was severely injured. He was buried in Lahore near the Anarkali Bazaar."
    },
    {
        "question": "'Lakh Baksh' was a title given to ruler",
        "options": [
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Raziya",
            "Qutb-din-Aibak"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "d",
        "note": "Gradually, as Sultan Ghori concentrated on Central Asia after 1192, he was given the independent charge of the conquests in India. Qutb-ud-din Aibak gave large sums of money in charity, thus earning the name LAKH BAKSH or giver of lakhs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Razia Sultan, the first woman to sit on the throne of Delhi, was the daughter of which Sultan",
        "options": [
            "Mohammed Ghori",
            "Mohammed of Ghori",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "Iltutmish became the first sultan to appoint a woman as his successor when he designated Razia as his heir apparent. However, after Iltutmish died on 30 April 1236, Razia's half-brother Rukn ud-din Firuz was elevated to the throne instead."
    },
    {
        "question": "Before assuming the office of the Sultan of Delhi, Balban was the Prime Minister of Sultan",
        "options": [
            "Nasir-ud-din",
            "Qutb-din-Aibak",
            "Bahram Shah",
            "Aram Shah"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Balban was the Prime Minister of (1246-66) Sultan Nasir-ud-din Mahumd and also the member of Noble forties."
    },
    {
        "question": "The first Sultan of Delhi to issue regular currency and declare Delhi as the capital of his empire was",
        "options": [
            "Iltutmish",
            "Aram Shah",
            "Qutb-ud-din Albak",
            "Balban"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Iltutmish was the first Sultan of Delhi to issue regular currency and declare Delhi as the capital of his empire. He was the third ruler of the Delhi Sultanate (1211 – 1236), belonging to the Mamluk dynasty. He conquered Multan and Bengal from contesting rulers, and Ranathambhore and Siwalik from their rulers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the Delhi sultans pursued the policy of blood and iron?",
        "options": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
            "Balban",
            "Iltutmish"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "Balban's policy of Blood and Iron: It is not without significance that out of about 84 year's rule of the Slave Dynasty, Balban's rule lasted for about 40 years i.e. 20 years as 'Naib' or Prime Minister but virtually the Sultan and 20 years as the Sultan of Delhi."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who among the following Tomar rulers, is credited with founding the city of Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "Anangpal",
            "Vajrata",
            "Rudrane",
            "Devraja"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "a",
        "note": "Anangpal, a Tomar ruler possibly created the first known regular defense - work in Delhi called Lal Kot - which Prithviraj took over and extended for his city Qila Rai Pithora."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the course of his numerous invasions, Muhammad Ghori (Before his conquest in the Second Battle of Tarain) was defeated by",
        "options": [
            "Chalukya king Bhima II of Gujarat",
            "Prithviraja Chauhan III of Ajmer",
            "Both (a) and (b) above",
            "(b) and the Chandela king Paramardi"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "During the course of his numerous invasions, Muhammad Ghori (Before his conquest in the Second Battle of Tarain) was defeated by Chalukya king Bhima II of Gujarat and Prithviraja Chauhan III of Ajmer. Muhammad Ghori was the Muslim king from Afghanistan. He wasn't aware of the power of the Chauhans. During the First Battle of Tarain, Ghori was defeated with heavy losses. However, the Second Battle of Tarain was won by Ghori because of betrayal from Jai Chand as there was enmity between him and Prithviraj."
    },
    {
        "question": "Prithviraj Chauhan was defeated by Muhammad Ghori in the battle of",
        "options": [
            "Tarain in 1191 A.D.",
            "Tarain in 1192 A.D.",
            "Chandawar in 1193 A.D.",
            "Ranthambor in 1195 A.D."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "b",
        "note": "The second battle of Tarain was fought near Thaneswar (Haryana) in 1192 A.D., between the Rajput Army under prithviraj Chauhan and the army of Muhammad Ghori. Prithviraj Chauhan was defeated by Ghori in this battle and this paved the way of Muslim Rule in India."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Muslim adventurer who destroyed the Nalanda University was",
        "options": [
            "Allauddin Khalji",
            "Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
            "Muhammad bin Bhaktiyar",
            "Muhamad bin Quasim"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "c",
        "note": "Muhammad bin Bhaktiyar was the military general of Qutb-din-Abak. He destroyed the Vikramshila and Nalanda University. NU was once one of the greatest universities in the world before it was destroyed by Turkish leader Bakhtiyar Khilji. Known for the great library and strong construction which took over three months to burn down, Nalanda University is once again ready to train scholars from across the world."
    }
]